I want to tell you three stories
أود أن أقص عليكم ثلاثة قصص
about the power of relationships
حول قوة العلاقات
to solve the deep and complex social problems of this century.
لحل مشكلات هذا القرن العميقة والمعقدة.
You know, sometimes it seems like all these problems
وكما تعلمون، يبدو الأمر أحيانا وكأن جميع هذه المشاكل
of poverty, inequality, ill health, unemployment, violence, addiction --
المتعلقة بالفقر، والمرض، والبطالة، والعنف، والإدمان --
they're right there in one person's life.
موجودة كلها في حياة شخص ما.
So I want to tell you about someone like this that I know.
وسأحدثكم عن شخص مثله أعرفه.
I'm going to call her Ella.
وسأدعوها إيلّا.
Ella lives in a British city on a run down estate.
تعيش إيلّا في مقاطعة قديمة متهالكة.
The shops are closed, the pub's gone,
أُغلقت فيها المحلات، وانمحت آثار الحانات،
the playground's pretty desolate and never used,
وأقفرت الملاعب ولم يتم استعمالها أبدا،
and inside Ella's house, the tension is palpable
أما بيت إيلّا فيسوده التوتر،
and the noise levels are deafening.
ويعلو به الضجيج الذي يصم الآذان.
The TV's on at full volume.
فصوت التلفاز يعمل على أقصى درجة.
One of her sons is fighting with one of her daughters.
وأحد أبنائها يتشاجر مع إحدى بناتها.
Another son, Ryan, is keeping up this constant stream of abuse from the kitchen,
وابنها الآخر ريان لا ينفك صراخه ينبعث من داخل المطبخ،
and the dogs are locked behind the bedroom door and straining.
والكلاب المحبوسة داخل غرفة النوم تصدر جلبة وضجة.
Ella is stuck.
إيلّا عالقة.
She has lived with crisis for 40 years.
ومنذ أربعين سنة وهي تعاني من الأزمات.
She knows nothing else, and she knows no way out.
لا تعرف شيئا سوى الأزمات، ولا تجد مفرا منها ولا مهربا.
She's had a whole series of abusive partners,
لقد كانت علاقتها بشركاء حياتها سلسلة متصلة من الإساءات،
and, tragically, one of her children has been taken into care by social services.
بشكل مأساوي تم أخذ أحد أبنائها لرعايته من قبل الخدمات الإجتماعية.
The three children that still live with her
وأطفالها الثلاثة الذين ظلّوا بصحبتها
suffer from a whole range of problems, and none of them are in education.
يُعانون من مجموعة من المشاكل، ولم يدخلوا المدارس.
And Ella says to me that she is repeating the cycle
ولقد أخبرتني إيلّا بأنها
of her own mother's life before her.
تعيش نفس سيناريو حياة والدتها.
But when I met Ella, there were 73 different services
ولكن عندما قابلت إيلّا، عُرض عليها وعلى عائلتها
on offer for her and her family in the city where she lives,
73 من الخدمات المختلفة، في المدينة التي تسكن بها،
73 different services run out of 24 departments in one city,
73 من الخدمات المختلفة ل24 قسما بحيّ واحد،
and Ella and her partners and her children were known to most of them.
وكانت إيلّا وشركاءها من أكثر الأشخاص الذين يتمتعون بها.
They think nothing of calling social services
كانوا يعتقدون بأن طلب الخدمات الإجتماعية
to try and mediate one of the many arguments that broke out.
لن تكون حلاّ وسطا للحجج التي اندلعت.
And the family home was visited on a regular basis by social workers,
ويتم زيارة العائلة بانتظام من قبل العاملين الإجتماعيين،
youth workers, a health officer, a housing officer, a home tutor
العاملين المهتمين بشؤون الشباب والعاملين بالقطاع الصحي
and the local policemen.
وضابط الإسكان والمعلّم الخصوصي ورجل الشرطة المحلي.
And the governments say that there are 100,000 families
وصرّت الحكومات بأنه يوجد 100.000 عائلة
in Britain today like Ella's,
في بريطانيا اليوم، لها نفس حالة إيلّا،
struggling to break the cycle of economic, social and environmental deprivation.
تُكافح من أجل كسر حلقة الحرمان الإقتصادي والإجتماعي والبيئي.
And they also say that managing this problem
كما صرّحوا بأن التعامل مع هذه المشكلة وإدارتها
costs a quarter of a million pounds per family per year
يُكلّف ربع مليون جنيه لكلّ أسرة سنويّا
and yet nothing changes.
ومع ذلك لم يتغير شيء.
None of these well-meaning visitors are making a difference.
لم يُحدث أي من زوار النوايا الحسنة فرقا.
This is a chart we made in the same city with another family like Ella's.
هذا رسم بياني قمنا به لعائلة أخرى بنفس مدينة إيلّا.
This shows 30 years of intervention in that family's life.
هذا يُقدّم 30 سنة من التدخّلات بحياة تلك العائلة.
And just as with Ella, not one of these interventions is part of an overall plan.
وكما هو الحال بالنسبة لإيلّا، ليس أي تدخّل من هذه التدخّلات جزءً
There's no end goal in sight.
من مخطط شامل، لا يوجد هدف في اللأفق.
None of the interventions are dealing with the underlying issues.
لا يشمل أي تدخّل من تلك التدخّلات حلّا للمشاكل المذكورة.
These are just containment measures, ways of managing a problem.
هي فقط إجراءات احتوائية، طُر للتعامل مع مشكلة.
One of the policemen says to me,
قال لي أحد ضباط الشرطة،
"Look, I just deliver the message and then I leave."
"اُنظر، أنا فقط أُسلّم الرسالة ثمّ أُغادر."
So, I've spent time living with families like Ella's
إذن، قضيت وقتا وأنا أعيش مع عائلات مثل عائلة إيلّا
in different parts of the world,
في أنحاء مختلفة من العالم،
because I want to know: what can we learn
لأنني أريد أن أعرف: ما الذي يمكن أن نتعلمه
from places where our social institutions just aren't working?
من أماكن لا تقوم فيها المؤسسات الإجتماعية بعملها؟
I want to know what it feels like to live in Ella's family.
أريد أن أعرف شعور العيش في عائلة إيلّا.
I want to know what's going on and what we can do differently.
أريد أن أعرف ما الذي يجري وما الذي يمكن أن نقوم به بطريقة مختلفة.
Well, the first thing I learned is that cost is a really slippery concept.
حسنا، أول شيء تعلمته أن التكلفة هي مفهوم غامض حقّا.
Because when the government says that a family like Ella's
لأنه عندما نصرّح الحكومة بأن عائلة مثل عائلة إيلّا
costs a quarter of a million pounds a year to manage,
تُكلّف ربع مليون جنيه سنويّا لإدارتها،
what it really means
ما يعنيه هذا حقّا
is that this system costs a quarter of a million pounds a year.
بأن هذا النظام يُكلّف ربع مليون جنيه سنويّا.
Because not one penny of this money actually touches Ella's family
لأنه لا يتم صرف ولو قرش واحد من هذا المال على عائلة إيلّا
in a way that makes a difference.
بطريقة تحدث فرقا.
Instead, the system is just like this costly gyroscope
عوضا عن ذلك، النظام مثل هذه البوصلة الكهربائية المكلفة
that spins around the families, keeping them stuck at its heart,
التي تدور على كل العائلات، لتعلق في قلوبهم فقط،
exactly where they are.
ولكن دون أن يحظوا بها.
And I also spent time with the frontline workers,
وكذلك قضيت وقتا مع العاملين الميدانيين،
and I learned that it is an impossible situation.
وتعلمت بأنها وضعية مستحيلة.
So Tom, who is the social worker for Ella's 14-year-old son Ryan,
إذن طوم، العامل الإجتماعي المسؤول عن ريان إبن إيلّا البالغ من العمر 14 سنة،
has to spend 86 percent of his time servicing the system:
يجب عليه أن يضي 86% من وقته في خدمة النظام:
meetings with colleagues, filling out forms,
يتابل مع الزملاء، ويملأ الإستمارات،
more meetings with colleagues to discuss the forms,
والمزيد من المابلات مع الزملاء لمناقشة الإستمارات،
and maybe most shockingly,
وربما الأفظع من ذلك،
the 14 percent of the time he has to be with Ryan
14 % من الوت التي من المفترض أن يُقضيها مع ريان
is spent getting data and information for the system.
يوم خلالها بجمع البيانات والمعلومات للنظام.
So he says to Ryan,
لذا يقول لريان،
"How often have you been smoking? Have you been drinking?
"كم من مرة كنت تُدخّن؟ هل كنت تشرب؟
When did you go to school?"
متى ذهبت إلى المدرسة؟"
And this kind of interaction rules out the possibility
وهذا النوع من التفاعل يستبعد إمكانية
of a normal conversation.
محادثة عادية.
It rules out the possibility of what's needed
يستبعد إمكانية ماهو مطلوب
to build a relationship between Tom and Ryan.
لبناء علاقة بين طوم وريان.
When we made this chart,
عندما قمنا بهذا الرسم البياني،
the frontline workers, the professionals --
حدّق فيه العمال الميدانيون، والمحترفون --
they stared at it absolutely amazed.
وكانوا مندهشين كليا.
It snaked around the walls of their offices.
كانت معلّقة على جميع جدران مكاتبهم.
So many hours, so well meant, but ultimately so futile.
العديد من الساعات، ولكن غير مجدية.
And there was this moment of absolute breakdown,
وكانت هناك تلك اللحظة لانهيار مطلق،
and then of clarity:
ثم من الوضوح:
we had to work in a different way.
كان علينا أن نعمل بطريقة مختلفة.
So in a really brave step, the leaders of the city where Ella lives
لذلك باتخاذ خطوة شجاعة جدا، اتفق القادة الذين يعيشون في مدينة
agreed that we could start by reversing Ryan's ratio.
إيلّا بأنه بإمكاننا البدأ
So everyone who came into contact with Ella or a family like Ella's
لذا كل شخص كان على اتصال مع إيلّا أو عائلة مثل عائلة إيلّا
would spend 80 percent of their time working with the families
كان سيقضّي 80% من وقته على العمل مع العائلات
and only 20 percent servicing the system.
وفقط 20% في خدمة النظام.
And even more radically,
وحتى بشكل جوهري أكثر،
the families would lead
ستقوم العائلات بعملية القيادة
and they would decide who was in a best position to help them.
وسيُقرّرون من قام بمساعدتهم على أحسن وجه.
So Ella and another mother were asked to be part of an interview panel,
لذا طُلب من إيلّا ووالدة أخرى أن يكونا جزءًا من لجنة المقابلة،
to choose from amongst the existing professionals
للإختيار من ضمن المحترفين الموجودين
who would work with them.
ومن المحتمل أن يعملوا معهم.
And many, many people wanted to join us,
والعديد العديد من الأشخاص أرادوا الإنضمام إلينا،
because you don't go into this kind of work to manage a system,
لأنهم لا يقومون بعمل كهذا لإدارة النظام،
you go in because you can and you want to make a difference.
أنت تعمل هذا الصنف من العمل لأنك تُريد إحداث تغيير.
So Ella and the mother asked everybody who came through the door,
لذلك سألت كل من إلّا والوالدة جمييع من دخلوا عبر الباب،
"What will you do when my son starts kicking me?"
"ما الذي ستقوم به عندما يبدأ إبني في ركلي؟"
And so the first person who comes in says,
وقال أول من دخل،
"Well, I'll look around for the nearest exit
"حسنا، سوف أبحث عن أقرب مخرج
and I will back out very slowly,
وسوف أخرج ببطء،
and if the noise is still going on, I'll call my supervisor."
وفي صورة إستمرارية الضجيج، سوف أتصل بالمشرف."
And the mothers go, "You're the system. Get out of here!"
وقالت الوالدتان، "أنت النظام، اُخرج من هنا!"
And then the next person who comes is a policeman, and he says,
وثم دخل الرجل الثاني والذي كان رجل شرطة وقال،
"Well, I'll tackle your son to the ground and then I'm not sure what I'll do."
"حسنا، سوف أطرح إبنك أرضا، ولكنني لست متأكّدا ممّا سأقوم به بعد ذلك."
And the mothers say, "Thank you."
وقالت الوالدتان، "شكرا لك".
So, they chose professionals who confessed
اذن قاما باختيار المحترفين الذين اعترفوا
they didn't necessarily have the answers,
ولم تكن بحوزتهم بالضرورة إجابات،
who said -- well, they weren't going to talk in jargon.
من قال ذلك -- حسنا، لم ينويا التحدث بكلام غير مفهوم.
They showed their human qualities and convinced the mothers
لقد أظهروا جانبهم الإنساني وأقنعوا الوالدتين
that they would stick with them through thick and thin,
بأنهم سيقفون إلى جانبهم في السراء والضراء،
even though they wouldn't be soft with them.
حتى وإن لم يكونوا لينين معهم.
So these new teams and the families
اذن تم إعطاء الفرق والعائلات
were then given a sliver of the former budget,
جزءً من الميزانية السابقة،
but they could spend the money in any way they chose.
ولكن يُمكنهم صرف المبلغ بأي طريقة يُريدونها.
And so one of the families went out for supper.
اذن خرجت أحد العائلات لتناول العشاء.
They went to McDonald's and they sat down and they talked and they listened
ذهبوا إلى ماكدونالدز وجلسوا وتحدوثوا وسمعوا بعضهم البعض
for the first time in a long time.
للمرة الأولى منذ فترة طويلة.
Another family asked the team
طلبت عائلة أخرى من الفريق
if they would help them do up their home.
مساعدتها على تجديد منزلهم.
And one mother took the money
وأخذت أحد الوالدات المال
and she used it as a float to start a social enterprise.
واستعملته كبداية لمشروع إجتماعي.
And in a really short space of time,
وخلال مدة وجيزة،
something new started to grow:
بدأ شيء جديد في الظهور:
a relationship between the team and the workers.
علاقة بين الفريق والعاملين.
And then some remarkable changes took place.
ثم بدأت تغييرات مهمّة في الحدوث.
Maybe it's not surprising
ربما هذا ليس مُفاجئا
that the journey for Ella has had some big steps backwards
فلقد شهدت رحلة إلّا خطوات مهمّة إلا الأمام
as well as forwards.
وكذلك إلى الوراء.
But today, she's completed an IT training course,
ولكن اليوم، أكملت دورة تدريب حول تكنواوجيا المعلومات،
she has her first paid job, her children are back in school,
وبدأت أول وظيفة لها، رجع أطفالها إلى مقاعد الدراسة،
and the neighbors,
والجيران،
who previously just hoped this family would be moved anywhere
الذين كانوا يُريدونهم أن يرحلوا إلى أي مكان
except next door to them,
ما عدا أولائك بجانبهم،
are fine.
لم يُشكّلوا قلقا بالنسبة لهم.
They've made some new friendships.
ولقد قاموا ببناء علاقات صداقة جديدة.
And all the same people have been involved in this transformation --
ولقد شمل هذا التغيير نفس الأشخاص --
same families, same workers.
نفس العائلات ونفس العاملين.
But the relationship between them has been supported to change.
ولكن تم دعم العلاقة بينهم لتتغير.
So I'm telling you about Ella because I think that relationships
اذن أنا أخبركم عن إيلّا لأنني أعتقد أن العلاقات
are the critical resource we have
هي مصدر حاسم لدينا
in solving some of these intractable problems.
لحلّ بعض هذه المشاكل المستعصية.
But today, our relationships are all but written off
ولكن اليوم، علاقاتنا مهمّة ولكن مُلغاة من قبل
by our politics, our social policies, our welfare institutions.
سياستنا وسياستنا الإجتماعية، ومؤسسات الرعاية.
And I've learned that this really has to change.
ولقد تعلمت بأنه يجب تغيير هذا حقا.
So what do I mean by relationships?
اذن ماذا أعني بالعلاقات؟
I'm talking about the simple human bonds between us,
أنا أتكلم عن الروابط الإنسانية البسيطة بيننا،
a kind of authentic sense of connection, of belonging,
نوع من الشعور بحس الإتصال،
the bonds that make us happy, that support us to change,
تلك الروابط التي تجعلنا سُعداء، والتي تدعمنا لنتغير،
to be brave like Ella and try something new.
لنكون شجعان مثل إيلّا وتجربة شيء جديد.
And, you know, it's no accident
وهل تعرفون، أنه ليس من قبيل الصدفة
that those who run and work in the institutions
أن أولائك الذين يُديرون العمل في المؤسسات
that are supposed to support Ella and her family
ومن المفترض أن يدعموا إيلّا وعائلتها
don't talk about relationships,
لا يتكلمون حول العلاقات،
because relationships are expressly designed out of a welfare model
لأن العلاقات هي مُصمّمة من نموذج الرعاية
that was drawn up in Britain and exported around the world.
الذي تم وضعه في بريطانيا وتم نشره حول العالم.
The contemporaries of William Beveridge,
إنّ مُعاصري ويليام بفريدج،
who was the architect of the first welfare state
مهندس دولة الرفاهية الأولى،
and the author of the Beveridge Report,
ومؤلف تقرير بيفيريدج،
had little faith in what they called the average sensual or emotional man.
كانوا يؤمنون قليلا بما سموه الرجل العادي الحسّي والعاطفي.
Instead, they trusted this idea of the impersonal system
ولكن عوضا عن ذلك، وثقوا بفكرة النظام غير الشخصي
and the bureaucrat who would be detached and work in this system.
والبيروقراطي الذي من شأنه أن يكون معزولا ويعمل في هذا النظام.
And the impact of Beveridge
وأثر بيفيريدج
on the way the modern state sees social issues
على الطريقة التي تنظر بها الدولة الحديثة للقضايا الإجتماعية
just can't be underestimated.
لا يمكن التكهّن به.
The Beveridge Report sold over 100,000 copies
تم بيع أكثر من 100000 نسخة من تقرير بيفيريدج
in the first weeks of publication alone.
خلال الأسابيع الأولى من الإصدار.
People queued in the rain on a November night to get hold of a copy,
اصطف الأشخاص تحت المطر في ليلة نوفمبر للحصول على نسخة،
and it was read across the country, across the colonies, across Europe,
ولقد تمت قراءته في جميع أنحاء البلاد والمستعمرات وفي جميع أنحاء أوروبا،
across the United States of America,
وفي جميع أنحاء الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
and it had this huge impact
ولقد كان له هذا الأثر الكبير والمهم
on the way that welfare states were designed around the globe.
عن الطريقة التي صُمّمت بها دول الرفاه حول العالم.
The cultures, the bureaucracies, the institutions -- they are global,
الثقافات والبيروقراطية والمؤسسات -- كلها عالمية،
and they've come to seem like common sense.
ويبدو أنها تتشارك نفس الحسّ.
They've become so ingrained in us,
لقد أصبحت راسخة بنا،
that actually we don't even see them anymore.
في الحقيقة نحن لا نراهم أبدا.
And I think it's really important to say that in the 20th century,
وأعتقد أنه من المهم أن نقول أنه في القرن 20،
they were remarkably successful, these institutions.
كانت هذه المؤسسات ناجحة على نحو ملحوظ.
They led to longer lifespans, the eradication of mass disease,
حيث أدّت إلى حياة أطول، والقضاء الشامل على المرض،
mass housing, almost universal education.
السكن للجميع والتعليم يكاد يكون في جميع دول العالم.
But at the same time,
ولكن في نفس الوقت،
Beveridge sowed the seeds of today's challenges.
أثمرت بيفيريدج ثمار تحديات اليوم.
So let me tell you a second story.
إذن دعوني أخبركم قصة ثانية.
What do you think today is a bigger killer than a lifetime of smoking?
ما الذي تعتقدون أنه يمكن أن يكون قاتلا أكثر من التدخين طوال الحياة؟
It's loneliness.
إنها الوحدة.
According to government statistics, one person over 60 -- one in three --
وفقا لإحصائيات الحكومة، شخص ضمن 60 شخصا -- شخص من ضمن 3 --
doesn't speak to or see another person in a week.
لا يتكلّم أو يُقابل شخصا آخر خلال أسبوع.
One person in 10, that's 850,000 people,
شخ من ضمن 10، مما يعني 850000 شخصا،
doesn't speak to anyone else in a month.
لا يتكلّم مع أي شخص مدة أسبوع.
And we're not the only people with this problem;
ولسنا الوحيدين ممن يعانون هذه المشكلة،
this problem touches the whole of the Western world.
هذه المشكلة تشمل العالم الغربي بأكمله.
And it's even more acute in countries like China,
وأكر حدّة ببلدان مثل الصين،
where a process of rapid urbanization, mass migration, has left older people
حيث تسببت عمليّة التحضّر السريع والهجرة الجماعية في ترك كبار السن
alone in the villages.
بمفردهم في القرى.
And so the services that Beveridge designed and exported --
ولذلك تلك الخدمات المصمّمة والتي تمّ تصديرها من قبل بيفيريدج --
they can't address this kind of problem.
لا يمكنها معالجة هذا النوع من المشاكل.
Loneliness is like a collective relational challenge,
الوحدة كتحدّي جماعي من العلاقات،
and it can't be addressed by a traditional bureaucratic response.
ولا يمكن معالجتها باستجابة بيوقراطية تقليدية.
So some years ago, wanting to understand this problem,
اذن منذ سنوات، في محاولة لفهم هذه المشكلة،
I started to work with a group of about 60 older people
بدأت العمل مع مجموعة حوالي 60 شخصا من كبار السن
in South London, where I live.
بلندن الجنوبية، حيث أقطن.
I went shopping, I played bingo,
ذهبت للتسوّق، ولعبت البينغو،
but mainly I was just observing and listening.
ولكن في الأساس كنت ألاحظ وأستمع
I wanted to know what we could do differently.
أردت معرفة ما الذي يُمكننا القيام به بطريقة مختلفة.
And if you ask them, people tell you they want two things.
وعندما تسألهم، سيخبرك الأشخاص شيئين.
They want somebody to go up a ladder and change a light bulb,
يريدون شخصا يصعد السلّم ويغيّر المصباح الكهربائي،
or to be there when they come out of hospital.
أو يكون حاضرا عندما يخرجون من المستشفى.
They want on-demand, practical support.
إنهم يريدون حسب طلبهم، دعما عمليّا.
And they want to have fun.
ويُريدون أن يستمتعوا بوقتهم.
They want to go out, do interesting things with like-minded people,
يريدون الخروج، والقيام بأشياء شيّقة مع أشخاص يُفكّرون مثلهم،
and make friends like we've all made friends at every stage of our lives.
ويكوّنون علاقات صداقة ملما قمنا بذلك في كلّ مرحلة من حياتنا.
So we rented a phone line, hired a couple of handymen,
لذا قمنا باستئجار خطّ الهاتف، وعاملين من العمال الماهرين،
and started a service we called "Circle."
وبدأنا بتوفير خدمة تُسمّى "الدائرة".
And Circle offers its local membership a toll-free 0 800 number
وتوفّر هذه الخدمة لعضويّتها المحليّة رقما مجانيّا 0800
that they can call on demand for any support.
يستطيعون الإتصال لطلب أي ّ دعم.
And people have called us for so many reasons.
ولقد اتصل بنا الأشخاص للعديد من الأسباب.
They've called because their pets are unwell,
لقد اتصلوا لأن حيواناتهم الأليفة مريضة،
their DVD is broken, they've forgotten how to use their mobile phone,
لأن مشغّل أقراص الفيديو الرقميّة قد انكسر، لأنهم نسيوا كيفية استعمال هاتفهم الجوّال،
or maybe they are coming out of hospital
أو ربما لأنهم سيخرجون من المستشفى
and they want someone to be there.
وهم في حاجة إلى شخص برفقتهم.
And Circle also offers a rich social calendar --
كما توفّر خدمة "الدائرة" رزنامة إجتماعية غنية --
knitting, darts, museum tours, hot air ballooning -- you name it.
حياكة ولعبة السهام وزيارات للمتاحف والمنطاد -- سمها كما شئت.
But here's the interesting thing, the really deep change:
ولكن يوجد هناك شيء مثير للإهتمام، التغير الحقيقي العميق:
over time, the friendships that have formed
مع مرور الوقت، علاقات الصدلقة التي تكونت
have begun to replace the practical offer.
بدأت تحل محلّ المساعدة العمليّة.
So let me tell you about Belinda.
لذا دعوني أخبركم عن بيلاندا.
Belinda's a Circle member, and she was going into hospital for a hip operation,
بيلاندا هي عضوة من مشروع "الدائرة" وكانت ستدخل المستشفى لإجراء عمليّة لوركها،
so she called her local Circle to say they wouldn't see her for a bit.
واتصلت بمقرّ "الدائرة" لتخبرهم بتغيبها لمدة وجيزة.
And Damon, who runs the local Circle, calls her back and says, "How can I help?"
واتصل بها دايمون الذي كان مسؤولا عن المقر المحلّي "الدائرة" وقال لها، "كيف يمكنني المساعدة؟"
And Belinda says, "Oh no, I'm fine --
وقالت بيلندا، "أوه لا، أنا بخير --
Jocelyn is doing the shopping, Tony's doing the gardening,
جوسلين تقوم بالتسوّق، وطوني يهتم بالحديقة،
Melissa and Joe are going to come in and cook and chat."
وسوفي يأتي كل من ميليسا وجو ليطبخا ويدردشان."
So five Circle members had organized themselves
لذا قام 5 من أعضاء "الدائرة" بتنظيم وقتهم
to take care of Belinda.
ليقوموا برعاية بيليندا.
And Belinda's 80, although she says that she feels 25 inside,
وبيليندا التي تبلغ من العمر 80 سنة بالرغم من أنها تقول بأنها تشعر بأن
but she also says
عمرها 25، ولكنها قالت أيضا
that she felt stuck and pretty down when she joined Circle.
بأنها شعرت بأنها عالقة وحزينة عندما التحقت بمشروع "الدائرة".
But the simple act of encouraging her to come along to that first event
ولكن مُجرّد تشجيعها للإلتحاق بأوّل حدث
led to a process where natural friendships formed,
أدّى إلى عمليّة تكونت خلالها علاقات صداقة طبيعيّة،
friendships that today are replacing the need for expensive services.
علاقات صداقة تعوّض اليوم الحاجة إلى الخدمات المكلفة.
It's relationships that are making the difference.
إن العلاقات هي من تكون سببا في إحداث الفرق.
So I think that three factors have converged
لذا أعتقد أن 3 عوامل ساهمت
that enable us to put relationships at the heart and center
في تمكيننا من الإعتماد والتركيز على العلاقات
of how we solve social problems today.
في كيفية حلّ المشاكل الإجتماعية اليوم.
Firstly, the nature of the problems --
أولا، طبيعة المشاكل --
they've changed, and they require different solutions.
تغيّرت وأصبحت تتطلّب حلولا مختلفة.
Secondly, the cost, human as much as financial, of doing business as usual.
ثانيا، التكاليف، .....
And thirdly, technology.
وثالثا، التكنولوجيا.
I've talked about the first two factors.
لقد تحدثت عن العاملين الأولين.
It's technology that enables these approaches to scale
إن التكنولوجيا هي الداعمة لنشر هذه المناهج على أوسع نطاق
and potentially now support thousands of people.
ومن المحتمل الآن دعم الألاف من الأشخاص.
So the technology we've used is really simple,
إذن التكنولوجيا التي نستعملها هي بسيطة جدا،
it's made up of available things like databases, mobile phones.
وهي متكوّنة من الأشياء المتاحة كالبيانات والهواتف الجوالة.
Circle has got this very simple system that underpins it,
مشروع "الدائرة" لديه نظام بسيط جدّا يستند عليه،
enables a small local team to support a membership of up to a thousand.
والذي يُمكّن الفريق المحلّي من دعم الأعضاء الذي من الممكن أن يبلغ عددهم ألفا.
And you can contrast this with a neighborhood organization
ويمكنك أن تُقارن هذا مع منظمة ذات صلة
of the 1970s,
خلال 1970،
when this kind of scale just wasn't possible,
حيث لم يكن من الممكن بلوغ هذا التطوّر،
neither was the quality or the longevity that the spine of technology can provide.
ولا الجودة أو طول العمر الذي من الممكن أن تُوفّره أساس التكنولوجيا.
So it's relationships underpinned by technology
لذلك تلك العلاقات التي ترتكز على التكنولوجيا
that can turn the Beveridge models on their heads.
من الممكن أن تقلب نماذج بيفيريدج رأسا على عقب.
The Beveridge models are all about institutions with finite resources,
تتمحور نماذج بيفيريدج حول المؤسسات ذات الموارد المحدودة،
anonymously managing access.
والتي تدير الحصول على الخدمات دون ذكر أسماءهم.
In my work at the front line,
خلال عملي على الميدان،
I've seen again and again how up to 80 percent of resource
رأيت مرارا وتكرارا إنفاق 80% من الموارد
is spent keeping people out.
لم يشمل الأشخاص.
So professionals have to administer
لذا يجب على المحترفين إدارة
these increasingly complex forms of administration
هذه الأشكال من النماذج التي تزداد تعقيدا وذات صلة بالإدارة
that are basically about stopping people accessing the service
وتتمحور حول منع الأشخاص من الحصول على الخدمة
or managing the queue.
أو إدارة قائمة الإنتظار.
And Circle, like the relational services that we and others have designed,
ومشروع "الدائرة"، كأي خدمات للعلاقات التي صُمّمت من قبلنا وقبل الآخرين،
inverts this logic.
يعكس هذا المنطق.
What it says is, the more people, the more relationships,
والذي ينصّ على الآتي، كلما ارتفع عدد الأشخاص، كلما ارتفع عدد العلاقات،
the stronger the solution.
كلما كانت الحلول أقوى.
So I want to tell you my third and final story,
لذا أريد أن أخبركم قصتي الثالثة والأخيرة،
which is about unemployment.
والتي تتمحور حول البطالة.
In Britain, as in most places in the world,
في بريطانيا، كما هو الحال في أغلب الأماكن في العالم،
our welfare states were primarily designed
تم تصميم بلدان الرفاه
to get people into work,
لإدماج الأشخاص في العمل،
to educate them for this,
تعليمهم من أجل هذا،
and to keep them healthy.
وإبقاءهم في صحة جيدة.
But here, too, the systems are failing.
ولكن هنا أيضا، تفشل الأنظمة.
And so the response has been
وكانت الإستجابة محاولة جعل
to try and make these old systems even more efficient and transactional --
هذه الأنظمة القديمة أكثر فعاليّة والتعامل بها أكثر --
to speed up processing times, divide people into ever-smaller categories,
لتسريع أوقات المعالجة، قسّم الأشخاص إلى فئات أصغر،
try and target services at them more efficiently -- in other words,
حاول أن تستهدفهم الخدمات بأكثر فاعليّة -- بمعنى،
the very opposite of relational.
على العكس تماما من العلاقات.
But guess how most people find work today?
ولكن خمّنوا كيف يمكن للأشخاص إيجاد عمل اليوم؟
Through word of mouth.
من خلال كلمة.
It turns out that in Britain today, most new jobs are not advertised.
لقد أصبحت اليوم في بريطانيا أكثر فرص العمل غير معروضة.
So it's friends that tell you about a job,
إذن الأصدقاء هم من يخبرونك عن العمل،
it's friends that recommend you for a job,
الأصدقاء هم من يقدّمونك إلى عمل ما،
and it's a rich and diverse social network that helps you find work.
وهي عبارة عن شبكة إجتماعيّة غنيّة ومتنوّعة تُساعدك على إيجاد عمل.
Maybe some of you here this evening are thinking,
ربما بعضكم اليوم يفكّر،
"But I found my job through an advert,"
"ولكنني وجدت عملي عن طريق إعلان"،
but if you think back, it was probably a friend that showed you the ad
ولكن إن فكّرت أكثر، فإنّ صديق هو من أخبرك عن هذا الإعلان
and then encouraged you to apply.
وشجّعك على تقديم ملفّك.
But not surprisingly,
ولكن ليس من المستغرب،
people who perhaps most need this rich and diverse network
هؤلاء المحتاجين لهذه الشبكة الغنية والمتنوّعة
are those who are most isolated from it.
هم أكثر أشخاص معزولين عنها.
So knowing this,
لذا بمعرفة هذا،
and also knowing about the costs and failure of current systems,
ومعرفة تكاليف الأنظمة الحاليّة وفشلها،
we designed something new with relationships at its heart.
صممنا شيئا جديدا ذو صلة بالعلاقات.
We designed a service that encourages people to meet up,
قمنا بتصميم خدمة تُشجّع الأشخاص على التقابل معا،
people in and out of work,
الأشخاص العاملين والذين غادروا وظائفهم،
to work together in structured ways
للعمل معا بطرق منظمّة
and try new opportunities.
وتجربة فرص جديدة.
And, well, it's very hard to compare the results of these new systems
وحسنا، من الصعب مقارنة نتائج هذه الأنظمة الجديدة
with the old transactional models,
مع نماذج المعاملات القديمة،
but it looks like, with our first 1,000 members,
ولكن يبدو أننا مع 1000 عضو،
we outperformed existing services by a factor of three,
تمّ التفوّق على الخدمات القائمة بمعدّل 3 مرّات،
at a fraction of the cost.
في جزء صغير من التكلفة.
And here, too, we've used technology,
وهنا أيضا، قمنا باستعمال التكنولوجيا،
but not to network people in the way that a social platform would do.
ولكن ليس للتواصل مع الناس بنفس طريقة البرنامج الإجتماعي.
We've used it to bring people face to face and connect them with each other,
لقد قمنا باستعمال ذلك لجلب الناس ومواجهة بعضهم البعض والربط بينهم،
building real relationships and supporting people to find work.
بناء علاقات حقيقية ودعم الناس لإيجاد عمل.
At the end of his life, in 1948,
في آخر حياته، في سنة 1948،
Beveridge wrote a third report.
كتبت بيفيريدج تقريرا ثالثا.
And in it he said he had made a dreadful mistake.
وذكر فيه بأنه قام بخطأ رهيب.
He had left people and their communities out.
ترك الأشخاص والمجتمعات خارجا.
And this omission, he said, led to seeing people,
وأدّى هذا التقصير إلى رؤية الناس،
and people starting to see themselves,
وبدأ الأشخاص في رؤية أنفسهم،
within the categories of the bureaucracies and the institutions.
ضمن الفئات البيروقراطية والمؤسسات.
And human relationships were already withering.
وبدأت العلاقات الإنسانيّة في الذبول.
But unfortunately, this third report was much less read
ولكن للأسف، كان عدد القرّاء لهذا التقرير
than Beveridge's earlier work.
أقلّ من التقرير السابق.
But today, we need to bring people and their communities
ولكن اليوم، نحن في حاجة لإشراك الأشخاص ومجتمعاتهم
back into the heart of the way we design new systems and new services,
في طريقة تصميمنا للخدمات والأنظمة الجديدة،
in an approach that I call "Relational Welfare."
وفقا لمنهجيّة أسمّيها "رعاية العلاقات."
We need to leave behind these old, transactional,
نحن في حاجة لترك هذه النماذج القديمة
unsuitable, outdated models,
وغير المناسبة وقديمة الطراز خلفنا،
and we need to adopt instead the shared collective relational responses
والاعتماد بدلا من ذلك على الإستجابة الجماعيّة
that can support a family like Ella's,
التي من الممكن أن تدعم عائلة مثل عائلة إيلّا،
that can address an issue like loneliness,
وتستطيع معالجة مشكلة مثل مشكلة الوحدة،
that can support people into work and up the skills curve
ويمكن أن تدعم الأشخاص خلال عملهم
in a modern labor market,
وتُرفّع في مستوى المهارات في سوق العمل الحديثة،
that can also address challenges of education, of health care systems,
والذي يمكن أن يُعالج أيضا تحدّيات التعليم وانظمة الرعاية الصحيّة،
and so many more of those problems that are pressing on our societies.
والعديد من المشاكل الأخرى التي تعجّ بها مجتمعاتنا.
It is all about relationships.
كل شيء مرتبط بالعلاقات.
Relationships are the critical resource we have.
العلاقات هي المورد الحاسم لنا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)